Newton Cheng

newtoncscheng@gmail.com (316) 925-1935 San Francisco, CA LinkedIn: tinyurl.com/uc7ejk

Google Scholar: tinyurl.com/3phdrcpm

Summary

PhD student with research experience in theoretical physics and quantum information with 4 publications. Graduate coursework and projects in data science and machine learning. Highly motivated and excited to engage with challenging real-world problems in ML, AI, NLP via a combination of theory and empirical experiment.

EDUCATION

• PhD Student in Physics, UC Berkeley, GPA: 3.95

2018 - present (grad. 2023)

• B.S. in Physics (Honors with Distinction), Stanford University, GPA: 4.03

2014-2018

EXPERIENCE

• PhD Researcher, UC Berkeley

2018 - present

- Advised by Raphael Bousso; conducting research into quantum information, quantum gravity, quantum error correction, and quantum computing
- Planned and executed novel research projects ranging from 2 months to 1 year, yielding 4 publications with 3 forthcoming, both independently and in collaboration with 1 to 4 colleagues
- Project examples include fundamental structure of entanglement, and generalizing quantum gravity methods to general quantum mechanics
- Engaged in short and long-term project planning, goal setting, team management, and organizing and leading meetings with collaborators to successfully bring projects from conception to completion
- o 12 talks and presentations to academic and non-academic audiences from 2019 to present

• Graduate Coursework, UC Berkeley

2018 - present

- Graduate statistics and statistical learning theory, with topics including estimation, hypothesis testing, optimization, generalization, Bayesian methods etc.
- Project-based machine learning, data analytics, and natural language processing courses
- Experience with analysis, probability, random matrix theory, information theory, and related topics from mathematics

• Head Graduate Student Instructor, UC Berkeley

2018 - present

- Managed teams of 8-12 Graduate Student Instructors in executing novel teaching materials to courses of over 400 students
- Assisted in the transition to remote teaching, and the development of virtual resources now used across UC Berkeley Physics Department courses, reaching over 3000 students per semester
- \circ Assistant instructor for 4 undergraduate courses; developed and executed original materials utilizing research-driven teaching methods, resulting in $\sim 8\%$ improvement in student performance

OTHER SKILLS

- Mathematica, Python (NumPy, pandas, scikit-learn, statsmodels, JupyterLab; PyTorch)
- Extensive experience in technical writing and speaking for academic and public audiences

Publications and Preprints

- [1] N. Bao and N. Cheng, "Eigenstate Thermalization Hypothesis and Approx. Quantum Error Correction," *JHEP* 08 (2019) 152.
- [2] N. Bao and N. Cheng, "Multipartite Reflected Entropy," JHEP 10 (2019) 102.
- [3] N. Cheng, "Optimized Correlation Measures in Holography," Phys. Rev. D 101 (2020) 066009.
- [4] N. Bao, N. Cheng, S. Hernández-Cuenca, V. Su, "The Quantum Entropy Cone of Hypergraphs," *SciPost Phys.* 9 (2020) 067.
- [5] N. Bao, N. Cheng, S. Hernández-Cuenca, V. Su, "A Gap Between the Hypergraph and Stabilizer Entropy Cones," arXiv preprint (2020).
- [6] N. Bao, N. Cheng, S. Hernández-Cuenca, V. Su, "Topological Link Models of Multipartite Entanglement," arXiv preprint (2021).